<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good newes from Florence of a famous victorie obtained against the Turkes in May last 1613. both by sea and land: By the great Duke of Florence, the earle of Candale, and diuers French commanders and gentlemen heereafter named. Translated faithfully into English out of the French copie, printed with priuiledge at Paris and taken out of the Italian discourse printed at Florence.</title>
            <title>Relazione della presa della fortezza, e porto di Seleucia, detta Agliman, in Caramania, e di due galere capitane, &amp; altri vasselli Turcheschi. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00985</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118620</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853827</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853827</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19225</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00985)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19225)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 578:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good newes from Florence of a famous victorie obtained against the Turkes in May last 1613. both by sea and land: By the great Duke of Florence, the earle of Candale, and diuers French commanders and gentlemen heereafter named. Translated faithfully into English out of the French copie, printed with priuiledge at Paris and taken out of the Italian discourse printed at Florence.</title>
                  <title>Relazione della presa della fortezza, e porto di Seleucia, detta Agliman, in Caramania, e di due galere capitane, &amp; altri vasselli Turcheschi. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21,[1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffin for Nathaniel Butter at Saint Austins gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Italian original has title: Relazione della presa della fortezza, e porto di Seleucia, detta Agliman, in Caramania, e di due galere capitane, &amp; altri vasselli Turcheschi.</note>
                  <note>Includes a translation of the French King's privilege to publish granted to Pierre Portier.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Florence (Italy) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  History --  1453-1683.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19225:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19225:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Good Newes from Florence: OF A FAMOVS <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ICTORIE OBTAINED againſt the Turkes in May laſt 1613. both by Sea and Land:</p>
            <p>By the great Duke of <hi>FLORENCE,</hi> the Earle of CANDALE, and diuers French Commanders and Gentlemen heereafter named.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated faithfully into Engliſh out of the French copie, printed with priuiledge at <hi>Paris</hi> and taken out of the Italian diſcourſe printed at <hi>Florence.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device?</figDesc>
               <p>VERITAS FILIA TEMPORIS</p>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Edward Griffin</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter</hi> at <hi>Saint Auſtins gate,</hi> 1614.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:19225:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19225:2"/>
            <head>A RELATION OF the taking of the Hauen and fortreſſe of <hi>SELEVCIA</hi> called <hi>AGLIMAN</hi> in CARAMANIA, and of two Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Gallies and other ſhips of the TVRKES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great Duke <hi>Coſmo</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, heire of the valour and glorie of his moſt princely Anceſtors as well as of their faire and flouriſhing States in <hi>Tuſcanie,</hi> knowing in himſelfe hee had as great an inclination and as much obligation towards all high &amp; great attempts in generall, and particularly thoſe that were for the ſea, as he ſaw himſelfe left with few oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions and little meanes for the ſame, hauing beene preuented therein by the ambitious va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of his father <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> which ſeemed to haue left after him nothing of any poſſibilitie,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19225:3"/>or ſuch as was full of extreme difficulties: hee ſeeing that (I ſay) fell not a crying with that <hi>Alexander</hi> which firſt got himſelfe the name of <hi>Great,</hi> but rather the more mooued with lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable emulation, endeuoureth himſelfe daily to follow the victories of his father, and if poſſible be, to raiſe them vp to the top of all perfection.</p>
            <p>For this effect being reſolued to giue ouer thoſe flyings on the ſea, and vtterly tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the faire enterpriſes by land, after hee had made a moſt curious fearch and examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the faireſt and hardeſt among them, the firſt he iudged worthy of himſelfe was this of <hi>Agliman,</hi> a fortreſſe of <hi>Caramania</hi> or <hi>Cilicia:</hi> a Country indeed which in old time hath had two moſt famous Cities, <hi>Tarſus</hi> the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan thereof and <hi>S. Pauls</hi> country, and <hi>Seleucia</hi> with the port and hauen thereof, now adaies called <hi>Agliman;</hi> from thence ſailed out armies for ſea the moſt ſtrange and formidable that euer were heard of. Hiſtorie tels vs, that the Pyrates which heeretofore there aſſembled, did ſet out together ſometimes more than a thouſand great ſhips, ſo ſumptuouſly furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19225:3"/>that many had their ſailes of purple, the roapes and gables of gold, and the oares ſet with ſiluer, that by their inrodes and ſcourings they had ſpoiled and ruinated aboue foure hundred townes, and broken and marred all the trading and commerce thorowout the Mediterranean ſea, ſo that proud <hi>Rome</hi> did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge by them ſhe was not vnuincible as ſhe thought, and was forced then to ſet out againſt them that great Nauie whereof <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peius</hi> the great was Admirall. This great Duke then aſpired to the ſame place on the which formerly <hi>Pompeius</hi> deſeigned his great enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe. And though this noble obiect was more than ſufficient to mooue his ſpirit, yet the Chriſtian zeale and pietie was his chiefeſt and moſt regarded motiue. For vpon the walles of the ſame fortreſſe were ſet vp the heads of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie worthie and braue ſubiects of his, cruelly ſlaine when the ſhip <hi>Prospera</hi> was loſt by the ſtubborne ignorance of the Captaine, which being drowned in the ſame did eſcape the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarie puniſhment he deſerued. This hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible trophey which the Turkes had thus ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to their pride, ſtill kept a flea in the eare
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19225:4"/>(as the prouerbe is) of this great Duke, more than the victories of <hi>Miltiades</hi> in the head of <hi>Themiſtocles.</hi> And ſuch a pitifull pawne miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſtaked vp there touched his heart to the quicke, more than euer was touched the heart of that famous The bane for the loſſe of his ſhield. The Agah of the place did foreſee it very well, which many times endeuoured himſelfe ſo to deale at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that theſe heads might be taken away, aſſuring that they could auaile to no other purpoſe, but as baits or ſpurres to the great Duke to enterpriſe the ruine of that place. Now then ſuch hath been the enterpriſe which this yeere amongſt many others giuen in charge (according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome) vnto the Admirall <hi>Ingherrammi</hi> did ſeg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalize &amp; ennoble the fame of the great Duke. The Gallies haue beene theſe ſix: the <hi>Capitana,</hi> the <hi>Padrona,</hi> the <hi>S. Maria Magdalena, S. Franceſe, S. Stephano, S. Giouanni:</hi> the which well furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with victuals and all kinde of munitions for warre, manned alſo with ſix companies of ſouldiers, vnder the command vpon land of <hi>Sor</hi>. <hi>Iulio de Conty,</hi> called <hi>Montauto,</hi> with more than fortie Knights, and a good companie of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19225:4"/>Nobles willing to venture with them, amongſt the which was reckoned <hi>Don Pietro di Medicis.</hi> They did ſet out the laſt day of March from the port of <hi>Ligorn,</hi> after they had deuoutly called vpon the diuine fauour vnder the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie guidance and luckie preſence of the Dukes moſt excellent greatneſſe their maſter. The ſecond day of Aprill they arriued at <hi>Ciuita Vec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia,</hi> and there found the Earle of <hi>Candale,</hi> Duke of <hi>Alluyn</hi> eldeſt ſonne to the Duke of <hi>Eſpernon,</hi> a yoong Lord of ſome two and twenty yeeres of age, which burning with a generous flame in the loue of valour, and to be ſegnalized by the worth of warres and deeds of armes, the only meane worthy of himſelfe, and practiſed by his anceſtors, was exceeding deſirous to be one in this enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>Which his Excellencie vnderſtanding, had commanded the Admirall to receiue him, and to vſe him according to the worth of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and houſe whence hee was deſcended. Thus that yong Lord with fiftie others which accompanied him were ſhipped and taken in, amongſt which was <hi>Monsr</hi>. <hi>de Cipierre, Monsr</hi>. <hi>de Themines,</hi> the Barons of <hi>Momberault, de la Tour</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19225:5"/>and his brother, of <hi>Auenes, Deltour, Du Pleſsis, De la Motte Magnas, S. Cyre, Monplaiſir, de Loïeres, de Vick, de la Boiſsiere, de Verneug, de Villandreco.</hi> The tenth of Aprill they were at <hi>Meſsina,</hi> and the fourteenth departed thence, hauing well refreſhed themſelues and prouided all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities for their voiage. So they went run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Archipelag ſea, without any worthie exploit, vntill the ſix and twentieth of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, becauſe they could not bring happily to paſſe another enterpriſe they had vpon <hi>Geron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> a little towne of <hi>Natolia,</hi> which is held to be the <hi>Gerunda</hi> of the Ancients. They landed there by the fauour of the ſtilneſſe and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the night, but being entered there in due order, the next day morning they retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thence without doing any thing, hauing found the place abandoned by the inhabitors, which many moneths afore had retreated themſelues in another place for feare of the like ſurpriſes. They ſet on and went forward their iourney Eaſtward for many daies, euen till the 13. of May, without atchieuing any deed, but the prize of three Changuis, which are ſhips as bigge as Caramuſſals, and ſome
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19225:5"/>other ſhippings of leſſe bignes. The morning of the fourteenth day finding themſelues neere <hi>Namur</hi> (a place ſome other times ruinated by the Gallies) they tooke it for a luckie ſigne, and reſolued their enterpriſe vpon <hi>Agliman,</hi> and making on that way about the breake of day, they ſpied a ſhip ſome ten miles farre off. The Admirall knew full well what difference is betwixt ſurprizing and hauing in chaſe. But becauſe that ſhip was iudged to be a Galley for the forme of their ſaile, and for the obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie which as yet was great, alſo becauſe they held for certaine, if that ſhip ſhould eſcape, it would giue warning to the whole Coaſt: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that the ſituation of the Coaſt was ſuch, that by reaſon thereof and of a little Iland not farre from thence named <hi>Papadula,</hi> the ſhip could be well and eaſily had in chaſe, cloſe and from the ſight of the fortreſſe, hee with the Counſell reſolued it ſhould be chaſed and made on. Thus making towards it and well purſuing it was ouer reached and taken in leſſe than one houre. The ſhip was of a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable bigneſſe of them which are called Grips, and was comming from the port and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19225:6"/>fortreſſe of <hi>Agliman,</hi> and gaue intelligence that two daies before two Gallies of <hi>Cyprus</hi> were arriued there, the Captaine of <hi>Cerrigna</hi> of 25. Beys, and the Captaine of <hi>Paffo</hi> of 22. Beys, hauing broght the tribute which from thence is carried vpon Camels backes to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> The ſumme could amount to ſome 200000. crownes. Beſides that they ſaid that the ſame fortreſſe was very well fenced and furniſhed, and well garded, and that about it there was more than 400. horſes, and that but a little while after them there was to goe out one of the two Gallies, euen the ſame way, to come to the Iland <hi>Papadula</hi> to take a Maſt for their ſhip: for this cauſe the Admirall ſets forward with his fleet, and places it cloſe vnder the Iland in a place whence it could not be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, hauing ſet his ſcout or gard on ground. Whileſt they were thus waiting for the ſame, the returne was ſuddenly made, and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence giuen, how the Gallie had made to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſea more than twentie miles, and in all haſte with her Keeper or Conſerua was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating towards the Port, whence they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that they had beene diſcouered in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19225:6"/>their chaſe. Thereupon was made a great difficultie, whether they ſhould goe forward in their enterpriſe, or elſe keepe themſelues for a better occaſion; but all contrary opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſet aſide, it was reſolued to goe on and follow their deſigne. To this effect they made towards Port Caualier, being from <hi>Agliman</hi> ſome twelue miles diſtance, and arriuing there about ſix a clocke in the euening weighed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour hard by a very commodious lands end, and very ſecret, with a deliberation to goe out in the night in time that might be fit and ſafe to land. Towards the end of the night they ſent out their long boat to ſpie and diſcouer. About two houres after or little more they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne and report that all the Country was vp in armes, the walles furniſhed with armed men, the horſemen about the fortreſſe, and the two gallies with two other ſhips within the Port. There on againe aroſe a great doubt if they ſhould goe on, but notwithſtanding the manifeſt apparence of ſo great a danger, they had ſuch confidence in their great courage, in the fortune of his princely Excellencie, and in the helpe and fauour of God, that they confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19225:7"/>againe their former reſolution. They therefore take their way about three a clocke in the night in deepe ſilence, and afore ſix in the morning their landing was made ſome mile and halfe from the Port. The Lord <hi>Iulio Montauto</hi> did land with the <hi>Comte Candale</hi> and ſome other choice men, few in number, to take a view of the Countrey, and though that they had ſome mile and halfe from them ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Cauallerie or horſe men of the enemie, yet neuer theleſſe in any caſe he commanded to land, which was made without the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of any of the companies, hauing left only twenty ſouldiers for the keeping of each Gallie.</p>
            <p>The fortreſſe of <hi>Agliman</hi> is ſeated vpon a fine hillocke right oppoſite to the ſouth, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending it ſelfe from the top of the hillocke to the very ſea ſhore, in figure ouall, or like an egge, the vppermoſt end whereof is on the top of the hillocke Northward, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermoſt, at the hilles foot Southward. The wall is of very good ſtone, the morter lime and ſand, a fadome broad and fiue fadomes high, ſo that a man may eaſily walke vpon it.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19225:7"/>In the third part of the inward ſpace there is a croſſing wall, which croſſes thorow and ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the compaſſe of the wall from the Eaſt to the Weſt, ſo that it diuides the place in two vnequall parts; the leſſe is as it were a reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and retreat of the biggeſt. The going in is by one gate only place diuſt in the middeſt. In the girt of the walles there are fiue whole and full towers, and three halfe ones: the full ones are of a ſquare forme fiue fadomes euery face; the halfe ones haue one face of the ſame big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the other leſſe by halfe; their height exceedeth not that of the walles, except that which is in the point of the hillocke, which is eight foot higher: the firſt full tower is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether within the retiring place eaſtward; the other is alſo eaſtward, but halfe within and halfe without: within the halfe which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fouthward is the firſt gate; the ſecond is in the inward face turned weſtward. The third tower is likewiſe halfe within and halfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out of the ſame ſide ſome 200. foot faire from the ſecond: betweene them both is one of the meaue towers ſituate outwardly. The fourth is at the foreſaid top and point of the hill, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19225:8"/>makes as it were the corner by it ſelfe, being all inward. At the going downe of the hill weſtward the two other halfe towers equally diſtant from the fifth tower, which is halfe without halfe within, and directly oppoſite to the gates tower. There be fiue little ſtaires to goe vpon the wall; foure of them are of ſtone within the great place, and the fifth is of wood within the retreat. In this place were more than 300. fighting men, the third part where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of had ſhewed out themſelues the euening before. There was abundance of victuals and of all munition for warre, and many peeces of great ordinance. Without the place about a hundred horſes went vp &amp; downe, and within the port there were two Gallies, a Carramuſſall and a Greeke Brigantin with ſome hundred and fiftie fighting men: they had retired with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the fortreſſe all rowing people. The order of the fight thus was ordered and contriued by <hi>Montauto;</hi> For the principall gate and for that of the retiring place he appointed the companie of the ſhip <hi>Cappitana,</hi> and that of <hi>S. Stephano</hi> with the petards vnder the command of the Earle of <hi>Candale</hi> head of that troope,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19225:8"/>with order taken that all ſhould obey him. The order being giuen, my Lord <hi>Candale</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducting the point, ſpied a corps de garde of footmen and horſemen, whereof he gaue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence to the Generall, ſending word that ſtill he would goe on towards the fort, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what he was bidden, and that if the Turkes ſhould make towards him, he would paſſe ouer their bellies, becauſe the countrey was very fauourable and good for the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie or footmen. The Generall praiſed his reſolution, though many gaue aduice to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat within the Gallies. So the way was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed on, till they came within ſix ſcore paces of the place. Then was my Lo. <hi>Candales</hi> troope ſaluted with great force of Muskets from the towne afore him, and from them of the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies behinde him, and from them of the hill at his ſide, and with ſuch outcries and howlings of the Turkes, that many were aſtoniſhed at it, and particularly the ſea men which carried the petards, ſo that they let them fall and ran away. They were taken vp by the Baron <hi>Momberault</hi> and <hi>le Tiel</hi> a ſouldier of <hi>Languedoc.</hi> Being fifteene paces neere the place, my Lo.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19225:9"/>
               <hi>Candale</hi> met eighteene or twenty Turkes ſalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, which he ſet vpon and ſuddenly put to flight; but in ſtead of purſuing them, his aduice was to turne to the gate, to the which he ran amaine, thinking to haue found it yet open, but the Turkes with all diligence had ſhut it againe. Therefore he commanded the Petart to be applied, which quickly was ready, but not without the hurt and death of many: amongſt the which <hi>Dom Piedro de Medicis,</hi> which had done this honour to my Lo. <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> to ranke himſelfe in his troopes, was bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten downe vnder ſuch a number of ſtones flung at him, that he fell downe halfe dead. The Lords <hi>de Callonges, de Momberault, de la Tour, d'Auenes,</hi> and <hi>Deltour,</hi> had taken this charge, the one carrying the Petard, the other the hookes, another the Madrer, and all the reſt that was neceſſary to make it go off more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily. But as this ſernice was a doing, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant Maior came and cried out vnto my Lo. <hi>Candale,</hi> that they were all vndone, and that there was comming right vpon them a troope of 300. Musketers: theſe were the two Beys, which were ſallied out of the Gallies in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19225:9"/>port, through the naughty watching and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of two companies left by <hi>Comte Iulio,</hi> and by him appointed to withſtand them, and hinder their comming foorth: ſo that my Lo. <hi>Candale</hi> was forced to take ſome part of his own men and make head againſt that troope, leauing the other part for the Petard. But when the Beys ſaw him ready comming to receiue them, and almoſt at handie blowes, they turned away towards the mountaine, yet ſtill ſhooting and playing with their Muskets vpon him. My Lo. <hi>Candale</hi> would not follow them, and thought it was more fit and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to goe backe to his Petard, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly did play on and made ſuch a breach, that three men a breaſt might eaſily enter.</p>
            <p>Now for the tower aboue, the company of horſemen, commanded by Lieutenant <hi>Len Zour,</hi> &amp; the company of the galley of <hi>S. Maria Magdalena</hi> with two Ladders were appointed.</p>
            <p>For the retreating place towards the fourth, the company of the galley <hi>Padrona</hi> with a Ladder.</p>
            <p>And to the gallies and ſhips in the hauen, the company of the galley of <hi>S. Giouanni.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:19225:10"/>
            <p>In that order they marched, conducted by <hi>Sor</hi>. <hi>Iulio Montauto,</hi> and by Captaine <hi>Alexander di Taranta</hi> Sergeant Maior, the Cauallerie of the enemie being ſtill aſide of them on the top of the hill. They were no ſooner within a cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhot of the walles, but they were ſaluted from thence with pellets and arrowes liuely and thicke: being come neerer, there flew a ſhowre of huge ſtones vpon their heads. But all this notwithſtanding, their Petard plaied on very happily, as we haue ſaid, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond gate being opened, the Earle of <hi>Candale</hi> with his troope entered the firſt with a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous furie: and no ſooner were they in, but that they ran to the retreating place to applie there another Petard; which was done, and the effect thereof very braue and ſeruiceable. The Turkes as well at the firſt as at the ſecond Petard were ſo abaſhed and aſtonied, that they knew not what to doe, but run away and flie to the walles, towers, and fortifications or barricadoes which they had made in the ſtreets: our men purſue them liuely and preſſe vpon them on all ſides. The two ladders be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low were planted at the ſame time that the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19225:10"/>firſt Petard plaied on them. But one which was of the ſouth ſide being broken, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome hurt to thoſe that were vpon it, all of them ran to helpe the other of the ſouth ſide, where the Cauallerie of the enemie was charging them very fiercely; by the meanes of which ſuccour, they forced the horſemen to breake away, and tooke their flagge or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, and hauing planted the ladder againſt the walles, a great many of our men got vp, and then diuided themſelues into two companies to charge both the one and the other ſide, opening by force of armes that narrow way, and went directly to the towers, where they gaue many furious aſſaults. The ſquadron of horſemen and the company of <hi>S. Maria Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalena</hi> hauing had a longer and harder way to make, could not arriue before the effect of the Petards; at the noiſe and terrour of the which the Turkes hauing retired into the higher place, they of the ſquadron found a maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous reſiſtance afore, and were laid on behind very fiercely by the Cauallerie or horſemen of the enemie, and by the foot which ſallied from the Gallies in the port: by reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19225:11"/>the Lieutenant after hee had done as much as a worthy honeſt man could doe, with his braue Caualieroes, ſeeing that he could ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance nothing, by the aduice of the wiſeſt, he reſolued to goe thence and make towards the place where it ſhould be more neceſſarie. But as he was ſtaying the laſt in that retreat (like a valiant Captaine, as alſo he had beene the firſt at the comming on) he was ſhot tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row with two musket ſhots, and fell dead on the place.</p>
            <p>The company of <hi>S. Giouanni</hi> maſtered at an inſtant the two Gallies in the port, and our Admirall at the ſigne giuen came with his Gallies to take poſſeſſion of them in the port without any difficultie, and touched not the two other ſhips, becauſe they were of Greece. The fighting and skirmiſhing did continue ſtill with all the towers and barricadoes of the place, and the combat grew more and more eager from both ſides, ours being kindled with a braue courage and held vp with a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conſtancie of reſolution, and the Turkes hauing the aduantage both of the ſtronger place and of their deſpaire. Finally, God the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19225:11"/>giuer of victories, was willing to fauour his owne cauſe: and the Turkes by little and little begunne either to yeeld or to offer themſelues to the ſlaughter, and ſo the hoped-for victory was fully obtained, to the honour and glorie of God, and of his Excellence. The fight laſted aboue foure houres, very dangerous and bloodie, a good number of ours hauing beene loſt there in the place, beſides fiftie fiue which were hurt. The combat being finiſhed, and our dead brought aboord one of the Gallies, amongſt the which were found <hi>Monsr</hi>. <hi>de Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueil</hi> and the yoong <hi>la Boiſsiere,</hi> very much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for the great hope of his noble valour: the place was disfurniſhed of all the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, artillerie, munitions and commodities, and all carried away; and the houſes hauing beene fired, euery one retired into the Gallies, whoſe heads were preſently turned towards <hi>Europe</hi> with the two Captiues Gallies, all very rich, and with huge booties, as well for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken eight other ſhips with a great deale of ordinance, munitions, and merchandiſes, as alſo for hauing brought with them 350. Turkes for ſlaues, and ſlaine aboue 200. fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19225:12"/>for hauing ruinated that famous Fortreſſe, and pulled downe that horrible tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phey of 40. heads of his good ſubiects, and freed from captiuitie ſome 240. Chriſtian ſlaues; It was a thing aboue all which greatly reioiced the great Duke. The day after, they met with a bigge Caramouſall, the which though it was manned but with foureſcore Turkes, yet ſtood for the eight Gallies, and neuer would yeeld, ſo that the Captaine of the <hi>Padrona</hi> at the requeſt of <hi>Monsr</hi>. <hi>Candale</hi> was faine to make towards them; which did ſo well defend themſelues, that they killed and hurt aboue foure ſcore of our men, three of the which were ſlaine hard by <hi>Monsr</hi>. <hi>Candale,</hi> which alone of all the French had permiſſion to fight at the fore decke, and ſhot three or foure ſhots within ſix paces of the enemie, two of the which were ſlaine thereby. Finally, as the ſeamen of ours began to get in, the ſhip was ſplitted, and as many as were within both ours and enemies ſunke and drowned. Some other ſhips were taken with leſſe combat. Then they arriued at <hi>Meſsina,</hi> where all the people with admiration beheld <hi>Monsr</hi>. <hi>de Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:19225:12"/>after the rehearſall which the Admirall and <hi>Comte Iulio di Montauto</hi> made of his valour.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license__for_the_original_French_text">
            <head>Briefe of the Kings priuilege.</head>
            <p>BY ſpeciall grace and priuilege of the King it is granted vnto <hi>Peter Porter</hi> Merchant Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner of <hi>Paris,</hi> to print or cauſe to be printed, ſell, and expoſe the Relation of the priſe of the fortreſſe and port of <hi>Seleucia</hi> or <hi>Agliman</hi> made vpon the Turkes, with the mappe thereof, all tranſlated out of Italian into French: with moſt expreſſe inhibitions in his Maieſties name vnto all Stationers and Printers of this kingdome to print or haue printed, ſell or diſtribute the ſaid booke or Card, but by the will and conſent of the ſaid Porter, during the time of three yeeres, vpon penaltie of confiſcation of the bookes, as the Priuilege containes at large. Giuen at <hi>Paris</hi> the <hi>26.</hi> of Iulie <hi>1613.</hi> Signed by the Counſell Brigard and ſealed.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Porter hath granted and conſented, that Lague hay ſhall enioy the ſame priuilege. Done the <hi>30.</hi> of Iulie <hi>1613.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
